<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection, or narative, sent to His Highness, the Lord Protector of the Common-Wealth of England, Scotland, &amp; Ireland, &amp;c. concerning the bloody and barbarous massacres, murthers, and other cruelties, committed on many thousands of Reformed, or Protestants dwelling in the vallies of Piedmont, by the Duke of Savoy's forces, joyned therein with the French Army, and severall Irish regiments.</title>
            <author>Stoppa, Giovanni Battista.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16255</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13150814</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13150814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 752:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection, or narative, sent to His Highness, the Lord Protector of the Common-Wealth of England, Scotland, &amp; Ireland, &amp;c. concerning the bloody and barbarous massacres, murthers, and other cruelties, committed on many thousands of Reformed, or Protestants dwelling in the vallies of Piedmont, by the Duke of Savoy's forces, joyned therein with the French Army, and severall Irish regiments.</title>
                  <author>Stoppa, Giovanni Battista.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: J.B. Stouppe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Waldenses.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Italy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:1"/>
            <p> A COLLECTION OR NARATIVE <hi>Sent to his Highneſs the LORD PROTECTOR of the</hi> COMMON-WEALTH <hi>of</hi> ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, <hi>&amp;</hi> IRELAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> CONCERNING The Bloody and Barbarous Maſſacres, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and other Cruelties, committed on many thouſands of Reformed, or Proteſtants dwelling in the Vallies of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Forces, joyned therein with the French Army, and ſeverall <hi>Iriſh</hi> Regiments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Command of his Highneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>H. Robinſon,</hi> at the three Pigeons in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1655.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his Highneſs the Lord Protector of</hi> ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, <hi>and</hi> IRELAND, <hi>and the Dominions thereto belonging.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OUR Highneſs having thought it convenient that I ſhould put in print the writings I have received concerning the horrible maſſacre committed upon the poor Proteſtants of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> I humbly dedicate them to your Highneſs, as to whom they do of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, not onely becauſe they were ſent me to preſent to your Highneſs, or that your Highneſs hath received them from other hands, but chiefly for that every one know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Piety of your Highneſs, and the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Charity you have teſtifi'd to the poor Proteſtants, the ſtrait Communion you hold
<pb facs="tcp:98106:3"/> with them, and the care you have of their preſervation, it ſeems as if your Highneſs were particularly intereſs'd herein. And ſo much the more, becauſe this cruell action was chiefely executed by the Iriſh, as in revenge to thoſe who have driven them out of their own Country for the cruell Maſſacres they there committed. So that every one believes your Highneſs will expreſſe a deep reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereof, and will endeavour the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and reeſtabliſhment of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of perſons eſcaped from this Butchery, who have choſen rather to quit their Houſes and Goods, than to make ſhipwrack of their Faith. This alſo is an occaſion, which God by his providence hath ſet before your Highneſs, to ſhew the incomparable zeale which you have for his ſervice and Glory, and to give to the Proteſtants an evident prof of the affection your Highneſs bears them, and to confirm them in the confidence they have conceived of your Highnes Protection. This all the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God expects from your Highneſs upon this occaſion, looking upon your Highneſs as a <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> whom God
<pb facs="tcp:98106:3"/> hath ſent for the repairing of his <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> I beſeech the Lord, who by the marveilous diſpenſations of his Providence, hath rais'd your Highnes to this great dignity, that he would grant you to be the Protector of the people of God in all Nations, as he hath in this, and that he would long preſerve your Highneſs, to the end you may imploy the power he hath given your Highneſs for the accompliſhment of his great Works, for the defence of his whole Church, the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them which remain, and the reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the deſolate and afflicted for the propagation of his Goſpell, the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Glory of his great name.</p>
            <closer>Which is the Prayer,
<salute>My Lord,</salute> of <signed>Your Highneſs's moſt humble, faithfull, and obedient, ſervant, J. B. Stouppe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the Churches of Chriſt, that do profeſs the pure &amp; holy Religion which he hath taught in his Word, that of the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes</hi> is the moſt conſiderable, as well for her Antiquity, as for the ſharp and continuall perſecutions it hath ſuffred. Her Antiquity is ſuch, that no man can truly find out her beginning: ſo that even her Adverſaries ſay, that the Hereſie of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> (thus they call their Doctrine) began in the Apoſtles dayes, and allwaies hath been in the Valley of <hi>Angrogna.</hi> But of all the Certificates which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Papiſts have given of the antiquity of the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and of their Doctrine, that of <hi>Reynerius,</hi> a Roman Inquiſitor, whoſe VVritings have been procured to us by <hi>Gretſerus</hi> the Jeſuite; is moſt remarkable: for thus he ſpeakes of them. <hi>Amongſt all the Sects that are in the World, there is none that hath been, or</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98106:5"/> 
               <hi>is ſtill more perncious than that of the</hi> VValdenſes <hi>or</hi> Leoniſtes, <hi>for three Reaſons; Firſt, becauſe it hath laſted longer than all others, ſome ſaying it began in</hi> Sylveſter <hi>his time, others deriving them from the Apoſtles. Secondly, becauſe it is ſo Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, that there is no Countrie where it is not. Thirdly, becauſe the Profeſſors of it live more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly before men, and hold all the Articles of the Apoſtles Creed, blaſpheaming onely againſt the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>and hating it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however this <hi>Reynerius,</hi> living about the end of the Eleventh age of the Church and the beginning of the twelfth, and ſo there being above 400. years ſince he did call the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> an old Sect, he ſhew's cleerely they had then been a time in the Church. <note place="margin">* <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher, de Succeſſione, &amp;c. <hi>Pag.</hi> 151. <hi>and</hi> 210.</note> Beſides it is certain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as we find in many credible Hiſtorians, that 1160. a great number of faithfull ſouls, call'd then the poor of <hi>Lions,</hi> or <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> becauſe they had been taught by <hi>Peter Waldus,</hi> a man of great Erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſingular pietie, being perſecuted at <hi>Lions,</hi> by the Roman Clergie, by reaſon of the Reformation, which he procur'd unto the Church, they retir'd into thoſe Vallies, where finding the Natives to be of their own opinions, they compos'd together thoſe reform'd Churches of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> which have ever ſince ſubſiſted: Which proves, that the reformed Religion profeſt in thoſe Vallies did not begin within an age or two of this, as ſome ignorant adverſaries ſay; but that it hath been either from the very Apoſtles, or from the
<pb facs="tcp:98106:5"/> firſt ages, and that the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> found there th ſeed of the true Religion, having nothing to do on either ſide, but to encourage each other to do better and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to ſet up the Banner of truth, in the view of the world. Since that time, thoſe poor Churches have always been the mark for worldlings to ſhoot at, and ſpend againſt them all the arrows of their malice. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than hath done all he could againſt them, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath ſpar'd nothing to deſtroy them, fires have been kindled, and flames blown up, to reduce them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſhes: they have had experiments of the barbarous crueltie of men. And as there is no war ſo bloudie, as that which is undertaken in hatred of Religion; ſo to ſuffer proſcriptions and exiles, confiſcations of goods, and impriſoning, torturing, and killing of bodies have been the ordinary excerciſes of the faithfull in thoſe Countries. Yet notwithſtanding the great Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres acted therein from Age to Age, God by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath allwaies preſerved a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, which made up many fine and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Churches, although they were alwaies under the Croſs.</p>
            <p>I will not enlarge my diſcourſe, to make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the perſecutions they have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſince a large Volume would not ſuffice for that I will only ſay ſomething of thoſe evills they have been expoſed to theſe two laſt years. There was great probabillity they ſhould of late, in the time of their Princes Coronation, enioy ſome quietneſs and tranbuillity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſince they had obtained the confirmation
<pb facs="tcp:98106:6"/> of their Poſſeſſions and old Priviledges; but they were ſoon fruſtrate of their hope; For the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Popes ſervants and Agents did work ſo cunningly, that they were deprived of the benefit of thoſe Priviledges; Commerce was forbidden them, many men driven out of their Habitations, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the publication of a <hi>Croiſade,</hi> they were 1653. aſſaulted by a great Army, which had wholly extirpated them, if God had not aſſiſted them by an extraordinary Rain, which did oppoſe the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of their Adverſaries, and made them vain. And becauſe this bloody Deſign did not ſucceed them well, they endeavoured afterwards to ruin wholly thoſe faithfull perſons by extraordinary Impoſitions and Burthens much above their own ſtrength, and which were not ſet upon the Papiſts in thoſe parts. Thus they did engage them unto great expences to obtain again the Confirmation of their Priviledges, and being obtained, their Enemies exacted from them prodigious ſummes of mony to have it ſealed. Yea, the matter was brought to that height of injuſtice, to make them bear the charges of thoſe, who were come to fight and ruin them. Beſides all that, there being a French Army in thoſe parts, it was ſent to take its winte quarters in the midſt of thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which thus were wholly deprived of what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained for their ſubſiſtence.</p>
            <p>But all that was but a beginning of greater ſorrow: for if they had then cauſe to grone and ſigh, they have had ſince occaſions to ſhed whole ſtreame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of teares;
<pb facs="tcp:98106:6"/> ſince they have try'd, how far the crueltie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of truth may go, and found that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fidelitie nor law in the behalf of thoſe, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſse true Chriſtianity in thoſe Vallies. They thought, they had in ſome ſort ſtill'd the Sea, and that a bleſſed Calme had ſucceeded the furious Storm, when after a long Negotiation, in which they had conſumed great ſummes, they had obtained of their Prince the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of their antient Priviledges. But they were ſoon deceiv'd of their hopes; for inſtead of keeping promiſes to them, Orders came, as from their Prince, againſt all thoſe of the Reformed Religion dwelling in <hi>Luſerne, Luſernette, Bubiane, Fenil, Bricheret, St. John, St. Second, La Tour,</hi> and <hi>Campigli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which is the beſt and moſt fruitfull ground in the Valley of <hi>Luſerne,</hi> as being in the plain, with a ſtrict Injunction to quit their habitations within thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daies, or go to Maſſe upon pain of Life and Confiſcation of their Goods; Proceedings directly contrary to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions or Grants of their Prince, twice confirmed by the preſent Duke, with his expreſſe Declaration not to change any thing therein. The Miniſter deſigned and ſent for the execution of that cruell Order hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one <hi>Andrew Guaſtaldo,</hi> who hath the Title of <hi>the Keeper of the Catholick Faith againſt the Hereticks of the Vallies;</hi> and who is likewiſe one of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill <hi>de propaganda fide,</hi> lately erected at <hi>Turin.</hi> He cauſed theſe Orders to be publiſhed in the places alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy named, the 25th. of <hi>January</hi> laſt paſt, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the extraordinary Snow and Rain, which
<pb facs="tcp:98106:7"/> then cauſed great Inundations or overflowings of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he (with the greateſt Inhumanity that can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) expell'd all ſorts of perſons without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of quality, or ſex, or age, and without commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of women with child, and lying in, nor of the ſick and weak, nor of old perſons and ſucking Infants. Many thouſands of all ſorts were expelled and forced to retire into the Rocks, there to be frozen or famiſhed. They did often addreſſe themſelves unto their Prince, and ſent many Deputies to beſeech him to revoke that Order, producing their moſt juſt complaints, and ſhewing their Reaſons in all humility; But all without effect, becauſe their Judges were their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and that thoſe, before whom their Cauſe was h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard, were members of the ſaid Councill <hi>de propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganda fide,</hi> and Slaves unto the Pope.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, theſe poor Fugitives complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but in vain, that their Goods were plundred, their Grounds laid waſte, their Houſes burnt and demoliſht, ſome of them went down to keep them, then preſently they were declared Rebells, and all Eares were ſtopt to their cries, and no hand would receive their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petitions; Yet ſome, to deceive them, put them in hope to be reeſtabliſhed, while by the means of the generall confeſſion of Papiſts to their Prieſts before <hi>Eaſter;</hi> all the men of <hi>Predmont,</hi> able to bear Arms, were enjoyned to be ready at a day appointed, that ſo they might ſet on thoſe Proteſtants; all being ſworn to keep that Plot ſecret. Every one was ready the 27th. of laſt <hi>Aprill,</hi> and with many the Roman
<pb facs="tcp:98106:7"/> Clergie met at the Rendezvouz, where printed Bills of full pardon of ſins were diſtributed to every man, beſides the ſpoyl of the pretended Hereticks given to them who ſhould deſtroy them. To this Militia of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edmont,</hi> the French Army, and ſome Iriſh Regiments, joyn'd themſelves, who together plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and wholly burnt all the houſes of the Plain, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Proteſtants, by the Order already ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>After that firſt furious exploit and ignoble action, the Marqueſs of <hi>Pianeſs,</hi> who did command that Army, would aſſault the paſſages and places of the mountains, where all thoſe did retire who had eſcaped the fury of their enemies: but ſeeing he could not do it openly by force, he reſolved to uſe a damnable policy, and deteſtable treachery to ruin them. He ſent therefore for the Deputies of <hi>Angrogne, Villar,</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> of the Vale of <hi>Luſern,</hi> and promis'd them, yea with an Oath, that if they would receive a Regiment of Horſe in thoſe places, and one of Foot in each, and lodge them for three days, no injury ſhould be done them. Thoſe poor ſouls, who believ'd him not capable of ſo black a treachery, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their ſubmiſſion to his Highneſs Orders, receiv'd thoſe wicked Regiments, which were no ſooner in, but the whole Army did follow, and preſently began their work, and put all to fire and ſword, making an horrible ſlaughter of all they found, without diſtinction of quality, age or ſex, young and old, men, women and children, rich and poor, were all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently kill'd, although by very different torments, and with ſuch cruelties, as can hardly be imagin'd. Many were burnt alive, ſome hang'd by the feet to a tree; Others torn in pieces, divers were ſtrangely ſlaſht and cut, then Salt ane Pepper being laid on their wounds, and their Shirts put on again, they were burnt in that ſort, and ſo made Martyrs in an unknown way to all preceding Tyrants and Monſters. Some being ſtript naked, and tyed head and legs together, were tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled down the Mountains. Others were nail'd unto the ground through the belly with ſtakes, and others were ſpit through
<pb facs="tcp:98106:8"/> the fundament, after the manner of the Turks, and others through the middle. Many women having firſt been raviſh'd, and endured divers outrages and ignominies, had afterwards their heads chopt off. A great number of little children have been barbarouſly butcher'd, ſome being caſt down head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long from high places, others pull'd aſunder by two Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who held them by the feet, and a third ſort had their brains daſht out. Finally, ſuch ſtrange cruel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies have been us'd againſt them, as were unknown to the very Heathen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, far from being exercis'd by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>This butchery being ended there, they went to the Vale of <hi>Perouſe</hi> and St. <hi>Martins,</hi> where upon pain of death they commanded all Proteſtants to go to Maſs, or to quit the Country within 24 hours. They left their goods and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did all quietly depart, except ſome few who turn'd Papiſts. But notwithſtanding their quiet retreat, all their houſes were burnt, that ſo they might never return, even as it had been acted in the Valley of <hi>Lucerna.</hi> Thus the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion hath been wholly rooted out of the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont</hi> by ſlaughters and baniſhments, and nothing hath been left there, but for the Roman Catholicks.</p>
            <p>Yet though there be about 6000 of them barbarouſly murthered, or that dyed ſince by cold, famine or other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, there are above ſixteen thouſand of thoſe, who ſav'd their lives from the Maſſacre acted on their brethren in the Vale of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> and who have been expell'd out of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe</hi> and St. <hi>Martin,</hi> who all retir'd into the Vales of <hi>Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Queeras,</hi> deprived of all goods, and all equally redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced unto an extreme want, ſubſiſting even by the charitable helps of the Churches, who did receive them, or of few others, who have ſent them their alms. In the mean time, as we ought not to doubt, but that God will revenge the blood of thoſe, who have been ſo barbarouſly butcher'd: ſo is it the duty of all the faithfull, to have a true compaſſion of the calamities of thoſe who remain, and are baniſht for the cauſe of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:98106:8"/> to implore God's aſſiſtance by ſupplications and prayers, for their preſervation and deliverance; and finally to communicate their Goods to them for their relief. Indeed as we are all members of one and the ſame Body, and oblig'd to be ſenſible of the Evills of one another, we ought above all to be lively toucht by the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of thoſe faithfull witneſſes of Jeſus, who have ſuffer'd for his ſake to maintain his truth, and the profeſsion of his Goſpell. It had been eaſy for them all to preſerve their Goods, and acquire new poſſeſſions, if they had been willing to make a Shipwrack of their Faith: If the ſpirit of Chriſt dwell in us, that ſame ſpirit, who quickens us all, and hath fortified thoſe faithfull ſouls in their ſufferring diſgraces and loſſes for God, ought alſo to move us to ſuccour them with all our power.</p>
            <p>What they humbly deſire of us, is neither to enrich themſelves, nor to make us beggars. They beg onely a ſmall part of our abundance; not to imploy it in exceſs or riot, but in the preſervation of their lives, which they are in danger to loſe through want. If we have a true horrour of the cruelty of their bloody enemies, how can we refuſe them what Chriſt doth ask of us for their conſolation? Who fails in ſo juſt a duty, inſtead of ſhewing himſelf a friend to Chriſt, and to his Saints perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for him, declares himſelf half their enemy, and ſeems to embrace the party of their Perſecutors in their deteſtable cruelty. For if thoſe inhumane Papiſts have unjuſtly ſpoyl'd them of all their goods, we ſhould approve what they have done in not affording them what's neceſſary for their ſubſiſtence. If (as 'tis very true) they have ſinned againſt our Brethren, through malice and rage, let us beware to make our ſelves guilty towards them, through our hardneſs and want of compaſſion. If they have ſtript them, and almoſt ſtarv'd them, ſhall we, who (by Gods grace) are well cloathed and fed, leave them both naked and hungry? If their Enemies have wounded them, may we not paſs for their falſe Friends, if we give them no ſalve, but ſee and ſuffer them bleeding, without binding their wounds, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ſome remedies? If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe cruel Murtherers have taken away the lives of many, ſhall we refuſe to preſerve theirs, who remain after that great ſlaughter? Yea, in refuſing to help the living, are we minded to make their condition worſe than that of their dead friends?
<pb facs="tcp:98106:9"/> for it is certain, that it is a greater cruelty to make a man languiſh in miſery, and to ſtarve him, than to kill him outright.</p>
            <p>I hope that all faithfull Chriſtians and Saints of this Country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lively touch'd by the ſad and lamentable condition of thoſe poor fugitives, who are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake, will open them their bowels of mercy, and will give them liberally ſuch portion of their goods, as may ſatisfie their hunger, and help them to ſubſiſt. So they ſhall have in their conſcience the joy and comfort to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the reſtauration of thoſe poor Churches, which God hath rais'd and preſerved miraculouſly ſo many Ages together. Thoſe Sanctuaries they ſhall re-ediſie, will without intermiſſion offer their praiers to God for their Benefactors proſperity and ſalvation. Thoſe members of Christ will bleſs them for their ſenſe of their miſery, Gods Angells will rejoyce for their effectuall compaſſion, and God himſelf having (as it were) ſmelt the ſweet odour or ſavour of the ſacrifice of their Alms, will now recompence them with all his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpirituall bleſſings, and hereafter will crown them in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with Glory and immortality.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:9"/>
            <head>A Briefe Apologie in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Reformed Churches in the Valleyes of <hi>Piedmont;</hi> With a Narrative of what hath happened in the execution of the Arreſt iſſued againſt them the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1655.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas we are forewarned by the word of God in the Apocalyps, that the rage and cruelty of the infernall Dragon towards the latter end of the world, would be in no wiſe abated; but ſeeing his time of perſecuting the Saints to be but ſhort, be the more vehemently incenſed againſt them, the Reformed Churches in ſeverall parts, eſpecially thoſe next unto us in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> have very often heretofore, as well as now, had ſad experience of the truth of this particular. For, notwithſtanding that the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98106:10"/> who is Soveraign Prince of the Vallies of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> after a moſt tedious and chargeable Application made unto him, did by an edict expreſly promiſe, that he would confirm unto them an enjoyment of the liberty of Religion, and of thoſe Priviledges granted to them by his predeceſſors Dukes of <hi>Savoy;</hi> yet through the powerfull perſwaſion of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (as it is called) <hi>for propagation of the Faith, and extirpating of Hereticks</hi> erected at <hi>Turin,</hi> or rather by vertue of that Authority which they uſurpe over Princes, he ſoon forgot his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and beyonnd all mens expectatations one <hi>Gaſtald</hi> was ſent with a Commiſſion, who calls himſelf <hi>Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator Generall of the Catholick Faith againſt the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Profeſſors,</hi> affirming that he hath received inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Prince, wherby Command is given touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of the Reformed Profeſſion within the ſeverall Towns and Precincts of <hi>Lucerne, Luſernette,</hi> St. <hi>John, La Tour, Campiglion, Fenil, Bobiane, Bricheras,</hi> and St. <hi>Second,</hi> both inhabitants and ſtrangers, that in caſe they will not, within three daies imbrace the Popiſh Religion, they muſt for ever bid farewell to their Native Country, their Houſes, their Lands, and Poſſeſſions: adding more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that it ſhould be death without mercy, if after that ſpace of time any of them were taken in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>Hereupon, no ſooner was the time limited over-paſt, but immediately the Miſſionary Monks and Popiſh Prieſts ſent in upon them a world of Cut-throats and Villains, who not only gape after the prey like hounds, and hunt for ihe precious life of theſe miſerable Exiles, but alſo diſcharge their rage and fury againſt their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Lands by cutting down and rooting up the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Trees.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, theſe our poor brethren knew not where to complaine of theſe injuries, and lay open their Caſes, nor to whom, being deprived of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98106:10"/> poſſibility of making any addreſſe to the Prince; and if any offer to preſent Petitions in their behalfes, they are preſently ſnap't, and ſent away to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation for propagating the Faith, and extirpation of Hereticks;</hi> that is, to their Adverſaries the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Turin,</hi> the Prince's Confeſſor, the Abbot <hi>de la Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> the Prior of <hi>Rorene,</hi> and ſome others, who are politick Penſioners to the Pope. Now, as touching this Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Proteſtants, whereby they are made to depart within three daies upon pain of death, into ſuch deſolate places, as are hardly ſufficient to receive and ſuſtain the Native inhabitants, the iniquity and injuſtice of the proceeding appears even in this, that the poor Proteſtants, through the influence of their Adverſaries and accuſers upon the Magiſtrate, were without hearing, or the leaſt Summons ſentenced to baniſhment, upon pain of death, without giving them any reſpite, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to make any Proteſtation or Appeal, unleſſe their Petitions were drawn in ſuch form as might pleaſe the Commiſſioner, who is the great Protector of this perſecution, and according to the mind of their Adverſaries, in ſuch termes as they ſhould preſcribe, whereby they muſt neceſſarily betray themſelves and their Cauſe; and then, after execution of the foreſaid penalty, they have been pleaſed to give ſome of the poor Exiles a hearing, and permitted them to plead their Cauſe, and that onely by a Popiſh Advocate or Proctor, who had been ſo charmed and terrified by the Clergy, that before he entered upon the Cauſe, he was faign to crave pardon upon his knees for undertaking to plead it.</p>
            <p>And as for the pleading, it was not managed before competent and lawfull Judges, but the Proteſtants chiefeſt adverſaries ſat in judgment, the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Turin,</hi> the Dukes Confeſſor, the Abbot <hi>de la Monta,</hi> the Prior of <hi>Rorene,</hi> and ſome others, devoted to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98106:11"/> the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> yea, and in the Arch Biſhops own houſe. Moreover, whereas according to certain Grants made by the Prince, leave was given to the Proteſtants to dwell in their wonted habitations, where they had a Toleration, and it remaines on their part to be proved, that thoſe were the accuſtomed places of their habitation, the matter was ſo handled by the Romiſh Clergie, that they endeavoured as much as in them lay, to hinder the Papiſts from giving any teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony on the behalfe of their Neighbours of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, concerning this their habitation, which at length our brethren made a hard ſhift to wreſt out of them, to the exceeding regret and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Clergy, and ſo proved at laſt by thoſe authentick teſtimonials under the hands of their Popiſh Neighbours, that all thoſe places, out of which they were driven, have been places inhabited by Proteſtants time out of mind.</p>
            <p>But to the end that it may more fully and clearly appear, upon what account of right or wrong the Popiſh adverſaries do incite their Soveraign, the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who is yet but young, to the driving of the poor Proteſtants out of their antient patrimonies and places of abode, in the midſt of a ſharp and terrible winter, and this upon pain of death, unleſſe within three daies after publication of that decree of perpetuall baniſhment, they immediately quit their native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or elſe abjure the true, and devote themſelves and their families to the Romiſh Religion. It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved (omitting the mention of their more antient rights and priviledges, and the long poſſeſſion which they have held beyond the memory of man) that in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>They are to be ſeen in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, ſet forth in French to the year</hi> 1561.</note> Edicts ſet forth by the Dukes of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the agreements, made for the Proteſtants enjoying a liberty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98106:11"/> of Religion, the limits appointed for the publick preaching of the Reformed Religion, do not extend ſo far as the dwellings of thoſe men that profeſſe it, nor are the limits of their dwelling to be contracted into ſo narrow a compaſſe as the places limited for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But that the reformed profeſſors have a right of habitation in thoſe places out of which they are now expelled, is evident, not only by an antient preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many ages, ſeeing their Fathers, Grandfathers, Great-Grandfathers, and other their Anceſtors, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited there before them, but alſo by thoſe very Grants and Conceſſions confirmed by Duke <hi>Charles E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> wherein it was acknowledged by publick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, that this habitation was derived to them from their fathers. For when he, through the inſtigation of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> had by a ſurreptitious d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cree com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to depart thence towards the latter end of the year one thouſand ſix hundred and two: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, being well informed of their right, he by an authentick Charter gave them leave to dwell there again; for the confirmation of which Charter, they paid ſix thouſand Ducatoons into the Duke's Exchequer, upon the 17<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt, Anno,</hi> 1620. and it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed again by the Prince now raigning, upon the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Decemberr, Anno,</hi> 1655. And yet now, contrary to faith given, upon the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>January</hi> laſt, in the depth of winter, not ſparing even women with child near de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, nor thoſe that had Infants hanging on their breaſts, they were all without diſtinction, both men, women, and children, driven out to wander through froſt and ſnow in a moſt bitter ſeaſon, without the leaſt warning or delay: And no ſooner had theſe old inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants quitted their antient inheritances for the ſaving of their lives, but thoſe ſavage Theeves that gaped after
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98106:12"/> the prey, preſently fell to plundering and ſpoiling their houſes, driving away their Cattle, felling and cutting down trees, or elſe rooting them up. In a word, they deſtroy all, and by this means attempt to drive theſe poor wretches to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> utmoſt point of deſperation; and if any man endeavour to withſtand or oppoſe them, they immediately crie out he is a Traitour. So I commend theſe miſerable exiles to the mercy of God, and the compaſſion of their brethren of the reformed Churches.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98106:12"/>
            <head>Andreas Galſtaldus, <hi>Doctor in Law, Conſervator and ordinary Auditor, ſitting in the Honourable Chamber of accounts of his Royall Highneſſe, and Generall Conſervator of the holy Faith, appointed to put in execution all orders which are publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the pretended Reformed Religion, in the Valleys of</hi> Lucerne, Perouſe, <hi>and</hi> St. Martin, <hi>and particularly appointed by his ſaid Highneſſe for this ſpeciall buſineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the power given us by his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by his Letters diſpatched to us in due form, ſigned <hi>Violetta,</hi> and ſealed, bearing date of the thirteenth of this Month; and in performance of the inſtructions given us, as alſo at the inſtance made to us by Maſter <hi>Barth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lomew Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staldus,</hi> intervening in the behalfe of the Royall Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; we ordain and command the firſt Sergeant or Bailiffe ſworn to make command and injunction to all the heads of Families, and to each particular of the pretended Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion, of whatſoever eſtate, condition and degree, no inhabitant excepted, poſſeſſing any goods in the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of <hi>Lucerne, Lucernette, Saint John, la Tour, Bobiane, Fenill, Campiglion, Bricheras,</hi> and <hi>St. Second,</hi> within three daies next after the publication hereof, to relinquiſh and abandon with their Families the ſaid places, and to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport themſelves into thoſe places and limits which by the good pleaſure of his Royall Highneſſe are preſcribed unto them, <hi>viz. Bobiane,</hi> the valley of <hi>Angrogne, Rorata,</hi> and Country of <hi>Bonetti,</hi> under pain of life, and confiſcation of their houſes, poſſeſſions, and goods which are extant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98106:13"/> without the ſaid limits, in caſe they cannot within twentie daies make proofe before us that they are Catholiques, or that they have ſold their eſtates unto ſome Catholiques: His Royall Highneſſe declaring, that it was never his deſign, not of his Royall Predeceſſours, by any act done or to be done, nor his intention, much leſſe his will, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large their bounds; and that if any thing hath been done or publiſhed to the contrary, it was both againſt his own orders, or thoſe of his Magiſtrates, but a meer uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation againſt the diſpoſition of thoſe Acts, as it is manifeſt; and therefore the tranſgreſſours have undergone the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties mentioned in his Declarations: Beſides that, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth intend, that in all thoſe places, and each of them, where they are lovingly tolerated, the ſacrifice of the holy Maſſe be celebrated; Prohibiting all ſubjects of the pretended Reformed Religion, to give any moleſtation in deeds or words, to the Fathers Miſſionaries, and thoſe that officiate under them, much leſſe to diſturb or divertany of the pretended Reformed Religion from turning Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, under pain of death; Charging, and particularly commanding each particular Miniſter of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, to ſee the forementioned injunctions inviolably obſerved, as they will anſwer it at their utmoſt perills; Declaring his intention to be, that the execution hereof be done by poſting or fixing Copies of theſe preſents, which ſhall be at the like value, as if they had been made and intimated to each in particular.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Lucerne,</hi> 
                  <date>the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1655.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Andrew Galſtaldus Commiſſioner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98106:13"/>
            <head>A ſecond Apology in the behalfe of the Reformed inhabiting the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory of the Reformed Churches, whom God hath preſerved in a corner of <hi>Italy,</hi> in the valleys of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> as miraculouſly as he did <hi>Moſes</hi> his Buſh in <hi>Horeb,</hi> not onely ſince the yeare 1100. when the poore <hi>Vaudois</hi> and <hi>Albigeois</hi> retired themſelves thither, well knowing that the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, namely, the modern, had no acceſſe there, but alſo time out of minde, that is alwaies, and from all time, as ſaith the Monk <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedere</hi> in his book intitled a Relation to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation <hi>de propagandâ fide,</hi> and as it is gathered out of <hi>Thuanus</hi> his Hiſtory and many others, is at large deſcribed in ſeveral books written to that purpoſe by Mr. <hi>du Perrin,</hi> and lately by Maſter <hi>Giles Paſtor</hi> in thoſe quarters; and ſhall yet further be ſeen, God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, by a ſecond Edition which will come forth, with an exact addition of what hath happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince; and very ſuddenly by as ample a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt as the caſe doth require it, that will be more particularly made manifeſt, which now in theſe few lines is but ſlightly touched, concerning their number, their extent, their fights, their deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Edicts, Priviledges and Conceſſions, by vertue whereof they have enjoyed the peaceable habitation, and the exerciſe of their Religion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98106:14"/> the diſturbances, which from time to time the Romiſh Clergy hath raiſed unto them, and the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances the Lord hath vouchſafed them, until theſe latter dayes, wherein he hath broken down their hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the Boars of the wood have utterly waſted that Vineyard, and the Hawks have chaſed and torne to pieces that Dove even in the very clefts of the Rocks.</p>
            <p>In the years 1560. and 1561. <hi>Emanuel Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> at the inſtigation of the Romiſh Clergy ſent a mighty army to deſtroy the poore Reformed of the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne, Perouſe</hi> and Saint <hi>Martin</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Piedmont,</hi> hard by the <hi>Dauphinè,</hi> under the command of the Count <hi>de la Trinité.</hi> That Warre was long and bloody. After they grew weary of it, both parties came to an agreement, bearing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſeveral other heads, <hi>the permiſſion unto all of the Reformed Religion to inhabit all places and lands of the aforeſaid three Valleys, wherein were any afore the Warre begun.</hi> In conſequence of which agreement and Conceſſion they were reſtored into <hi>Lucerne, Lucernette,</hi> Saint <hi>John, la Tour, Fenil, Bobiane,</hi> and Saint <hi>Second,</hi> which places are lower towards the plaine about <hi>Turin</hi> and <hi>Pinerol,</hi> as well as into the more remote places towards the neighbouring Mountaines of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and they have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved there and protected by their Princes until the year 1602. Then <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and Prince of <hi>Piedmont</hi> of glorious memory, after the baniſhment of the reformed out of the Marqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate of <hi>Salluces,</hi> gave leave to his Delegates to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh ſeveral Orders againſt the inhabitants of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98106:14"/> Valley of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> who dwelt towards the South of it, beyond the river called <hi>Pelice, viz.</hi> the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Borroughs of <hi>Lucerne, Bobiane,</hi> and <hi>Fenil,</hi> which are but ſmall dependences of the Church of Saint <hi>John,</hi> but would not ſuffer them to touch the reſt. And indeed it ſhall not be found, that during the former perſecutions, any Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> hath ever pretended that all the other places, nor any of them, of thoſe marked in the Order, be out of the limits of the habitation granted to the Reformed.</p>
            <p>It is very remarkable, that ſoon after, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1603. he made a Decree, whereby he ordered to thoſe of <hi>Lucerne, Bobiane</hi> and <hi>Fenil,</hi> who alone had beene turned out, <hi>to inhabite againe their houſes, and enjoy their eſtates, recalling all orders to the contrary.</hi> He confirmed the ſame by a Decree of the 29th of <hi>September</hi> in the ſame yeare, in the firſt Article. And he kept them in the poſſeſſion untill the year 1620, at which time yet they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtirre againſt thoſe of the ſame Lands of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, Bobiane</hi> and <hi>Fenil;</hi> but the clemency and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of his ſaid Royall Highneſſe was yet ſuch, that he no ſooner had granted the order for their baniſhment, but preſently he recalled it, and granted them againe a fine Decree, whereby he declared <hi>That he was willing, and intended that all the pretended Reformed</hi> (for ſuch are his words) <hi>ſhould peaceably enjoy their habitation, in all the places formerly granted and accuſtomed,</hi> ſuch as the aforeſaid were: <hi>Ordered that they ſhould be no more moleſted therein,</hi> and even granted them the enjoyment of ſome Temples pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be lower towards the plaine; then the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98106:15"/> of the preaching extended unto; and that he granted for a Sum of 6000 Ducatoons he exacted from them. All theſe have been confirmed by the Ducal Chamber and the Senate, and were obſerved during all the reſt of the life of the ſame <hi>Charles E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel.</hi> After him, <hi>Victorio Amedeo</hi> his ſucceſſor of glorious memory, left them alſo in the full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of whatſoever his Predeceſſors had granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and ſpecially the free commerce in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and the peaceable habitation in all the places which are queſtioned in the order which ſhall follow, having only deprived them, contrary to their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Conceſſions, of bearing any publick Office, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if his Father and Granfather had granted them that priviledge, for his part he was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to continue it; or as now the Marquis of <hi>Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> doth ſpeak, that <hi>graces of Princes are not unalterable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards, Madam Royall during the time of her whole Regency, hath yet preſerved them in the ſame ſtate without diſturbing them for their habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and even in 1638. iſſued out a fine Decree, bearing an expreſſe promiſe of a confirmation and obſervation of their ancient Edicts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> now reigning, by the grace of God, being come to his Majority, the Reformed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after demanded of him in all humility the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their antient priviledges. He granted them the ſame in 1649. with ſome ſmall reſtriction; yet the Reformed not having hoped any thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were willing and deſired to have the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Ducal Chamber, They had promiſe that ſo it ſhould be done, having received the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and agreed about the money, and kept the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98106:15"/> whole buſineſſe in ſuſpence, untill his Royall High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (becauſe the valleyes had refuſed him ſome hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to have the Maſſe ſaid in them, in ſuch Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, where there were no Romiſh Catholicks) ſhould have ſeized on ſuch as he pleaſed, <hi>ex Officio,</hi> as ſaith his order of 1650, as Maſter of the Lands. This being done, the ſaid Chamber granted them in <hi>June</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> 1653 and in <hi>May,</hi> 1654 not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the confirmation of their antient Conceſſions, <hi>to be as they were in uſe,</hi> as ſpeak the Decrees aforeſaid former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſed, <hi>but as they had been in uſe under his Predeceſſors, &amp; as they were found in their Decrees, without adding or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing.</hi> And there by he reſtored them to the ability of bearing publick charges, and the right of habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commonalty of <hi>Campiglion,</hi> and of the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of <hi>Bobiane,</hi> from whence they had been expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: But when the confirmation of theſe new Decrees hath likewiſe been granted, and the money disburſed, at the time appointed, when they ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, a Patrimonial Advocate was raiſed up, who alledged, that the Congregation <hi>de propagandâ ſide</hi> ought to be aquainted with it. The ſaid Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then oppoſed the foreſaid confirmation. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed applied themſelves again to his Royall Highneſſe, who referred them to the ſaid Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but they refuſed the ſame, as being their adverſarie parties: They were referred to the Marquiſſe <hi>de Pian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the head of the ſaid Congregation; they appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before him, as being chief Miniſters of State to his Royall Highneſſe; but he declared unto them, that they ſhould never expect audience, unleſſe they ſhould firſt paſſe a procuration, promiſing to accept and yield to whatſoever ſhould be ordained. They
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98106:16"/> anſwered, that ever they had dealt with their Princes by humble requeſts and Petitions, and never by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curations: He replyed, that without ſuch Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no Petition would be received; therefore they dreſſed ſuch a Procuration unto two Deputies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they grant them <hi>full power to accept of, and to promiſe whatſoever ſhould be ordained, ſaving only their Conſciences and their Conceſſions.</hi> He refuſed to ſee the ſame, or to receive it with that reſtriction; and on the 13. of <hi>January</hi> of this preſent year 1655. he drew, or cauſed to be drawn an order by the Delegat <hi>Gaſtaldo,</hi> who publiſhed the ſame on the 25. of that Month, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that thoſe of <hi>Lucerne, Bobiane,</hi> and <hi>Fenil</hi> (who formerly had been moleſted) and <hi>S. John, la Tour,</hi> and <hi>S. Second, ſhould within three daies forſake their houſes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pain of death, unleſſe within twenty daies they would go to the Maſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That rigorous order much ſurpriſed them; yet thoſe of the plaine to avoid the violence of their bad neighbours, preſently obeyed the ſame, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made their proteſtations before the Delegat, and demanded again, that they might apply themſelves to his Royal Highneſſe, and to have an act how they had appeared: It was denyed them &amp; all the proofes they offered of their juſt title of habitation in thoſe places, rejected, without being examined. In the mean while their neighbours pillaged, plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ruined their houſes, pluckt up the young Trees, and cut off the talleſt; They complained of it, and had this anſwer returned unto them, that if theſe exiled perſons would watch, and give notice of thoſe that were guilty, they would be brought to puniſhment;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98106:16"/> therupon ſome of them went down to keep their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Preſently they were declared Rebels, and therefore not a word more of addreſſes, petitions, or ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be heard of; they were left to ſleep for a while. In the mean time, by meanes of the Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion afore <hi>Eaſter,</hi> all the <hi>Piedmont</hi> is diſpoſed to fall on them upon a day appointed. The Father knows nothing of the Son, nor the Brother of his Brother, and yet the twelfth of <hi>April,</hi> without any gathering of Souldiers, or any foregoing preparation, all is found ready; All men able to bear Armes in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> with all the Clergy, came to the Rendezvous: Printed Bils were diſtributed among them, bearing a plenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Indulgence all pardon, beſides the booty to all thoſe that would goe and fight againſt the pretended Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. To the Army of <hi>Piedmont</hi> that of the French was preſently joined, which before quartered in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and was made to come over the <hi>Alpes.</hi> All theſe Troopes and Souldies did wholly waſte and burn the Plain, where the interdicted places, mentioned in the aforeſaid order, were ſituated.</p>
            <p>That done, the Marqueſſe <hi>de Pianeſs</hi> quartered in the Monaſtery of the Franciſcan Friers at <hi>la Tour,</hi> (who, as well as the reſt of their Brothers in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> are all Spaniards.) There he called the Deputies of <hi>Angrogn, Villar,</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> of the <hi>Vale de Lucerne;</hi> he much flattered them, and told, that as to them, they were in the limits which his Royal Highneſſe was reſolved to tolerate; that no harm would be done unto them, if only they would receive a Regiment of Foot, and a Troop of Horſe in each Commonalty, engaging his word, and with oath promiſing the word of his Royal Highneſſe; But threatning them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98106:17"/> in caſe of refuſal, that they ſhould be declared Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. The Deputies not having leave to confer about it, and ſeeing the French Forces, with all the <hi>Piedmont</hi> ready to fall on them, and hoping that the word en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to them would be performed, and that his Highneſs would not wholly deſtroy thoſe places, they conſented thereunto, came up with thoſe Forces, and forbad the Reformed to ſhoot at them; But they were no ſooner in thoſe ſtrong places, but the reſt of the Army fell on on all ſides, ſeized on the tops of the Mountaines, put to the ſword and fire whatſoever they met in their way, and did practiſe there the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, whereof the Pattern may be ſeen in the here an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed papers.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Vale Lucerne</hi> deſtroyed. From thence they came to <hi>Vale Perouſe</hi> and <hi>St. Martin,</hi> an Order was ſent them either to go to Maſſe, or to be gone out of the Country within twenty four hours, <hi>under pain of death, and forfeiture of their eſtates.</hi> They thereupon forſook their houſes, and fled into the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and thereby all gave obedience, except a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle number of ſmall people, who turned Papiſts; but notwithſtanding their retreat, their houſes were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to aſhes, and all the Country made waſte, as the <hi>Vale Lucerne;</hi> having thereby wholly rooted out the Reformed Religion in the valley of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> not one Temple, nor one houſe, neither man nor beaſt having been left there, onely for the Romiſh Catholikes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98106:17"/>
               <head>A third Apologie for the ſaid Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Calumnies falſly imputed to them.</head>
               <p>REceiving Information from a friend touching the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer made at <hi>Turin,</hi> I perceive thoſe enemies of the truth, the Vaſſals of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> who contrived it with no leſſe Art then malice, do follow their old courſe, and after the example of him, who is both a murtherer and a liar, yea the Father of lies, cover, and ſo encreaſe their cruelty by falſe Calumniations. For, whereas they would not ſeem to be unjuſt in this baniſhment forced upon the Reformed <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> they endeavor to aſperſe them with fictious and Imaginary Crimes, and yet dare not charge them expreſly with any one Particular in writing, for fear leſt the Parties accuſed ſhould diſprove it, which they know might eaſily be done. For, when the Proteſtants had made Anſwer to ſuch Accuſations as were brought againſt them by <hi>Gaſtald</hi> before the Duke's Deputy, he ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed thoſe Crimes were objected againſt them without cauſe, to wit, thoſe pious frauds or officious lyes ſpred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by the Monks and Prieſts, to draw an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the Proteſtants. <hi>Si accuſaſſe ſufficiat, quis erit innocens?</hi> If it be ſufficient to accuſe, who then can be innocent? If an accuſer only in general termes ſay a man is wicked, what Anſwer can be made in order to a Purgation?</p>
               <p>The Proteſtants for their parts, call God, Angels, and men to witneſſe, that they are moſt injuriouſly charged with thoſe things. Yea, they humbly pray, intreat, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech they may be brought to a Trial, that if any be found guilty he may be ſeverely puniſhed. But here the Romiſh
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98106:18"/> Clergy interpoſe, endeavouring with their Scare-crow of Excommunication, and threats of everlaſting damnation, ſo to terrifie their ſeduced people, that no Papiſt dare give any Teſtimony, though in things moſt evidently known, to cleare the innocency of Proteſtants, for fear leſt he ſhould be thought a favourer of Hereticks; And hereupon, thoſe Monks and Prieſts, the Contrivers of thoſe Officious lies, preſuming upon their own power, through the terror of Excommunication, and knowing very well, that no Papiſt will dare to give in any evidence for the refelling of their Impoſtures, doe with a brow of braſſe moſt audaciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and object whatever they pleaſe againſt the Reformed Profeſſors: But if the difference in Religion and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of parties were ſet aſide, and the whole cauſe brought to a hearing before impartial Judges, without reſpect of perſons, and if witneſſes might have liberty to give in their Teſtimony according to truth, without fear of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, all the Calumnies of the Adverſaries againſt the Proteſtants would ſoon come to nothing. They made no ſcruple to render them odious to the Prince, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing them of Rebellion, but the thing it ſelfe is clear enough to the contrary: For, thoſe Proteſtants that were ſuddenly driven out of their ancient Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, lived ſome of them quiet and ſecure in their Cottages; others wandring about in divers Countries, being ſcattered farre diſtant from each other, dwelt in many places but a few of them among great numbers of Papiſts, minding nothing elſe but their Plough and tillage of the ground. At that time they had no Meetings nor Commerce with one another. Every one of them with his poor family reſted in peace under his own Vine and his own fig-tree, until they were driven out by <hi>Gaſtald</hi> the Dukes Commiſſioner, without allowing them the benefit of any legal Proteſtation and Appeal. What univerſal conſpiracy then can be faſtened upon all thoſe men, who were diſperſed up and down in Towns, Villages, and Fields? That they lived in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98106:18"/> the ſeats of their Fathers, and their ancient Poſſeſſions, and that they had not attempted any alteration of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, nor in any wiſe exceeded the Bounds and limits ſet and prefixed to their habitation, they are able to prove by undoubted Arguments and infallible Witneſſes from the very place it ſelf. We underſtand indeed by Letters, onely of two Crimes objected againſt certain Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; of which the one was a fooliſh childiſh exploit of certain Boies, both Proteſtant and Popiſh, at <hi>la Tour,</hi> who upon occaſion of a marriage between two perſons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal years, brought out an Aſſe belonging to the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, to mock the Bride and make mockery of the Wedding; Whereupon the Monks took occaſion to wreſt the matter againſt the Proteſtants, as intended by them to the diſgrace and reproach of their Maſſe; but upon a hearing of the buſineſſe by the Prince's Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, before whom the Proteſtants made their defence, he acquitted them as innocent in this Particular, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that in time to come no further mention ſhould be made of it; Nevertheleſſe, the Monks are up with it ever and anon in other Places, where the falſhood of their Calumnies is not known. The parents of thoſe wanton Boies ought not to ſuffer for their childiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, much leſſe ought that whole Church, and the Proteſtants of other Churches; and if they deſerve Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for this, the ſame puniſhment ought alſo with as much reaſon to be inflicted upon thoſe Papiſts, whoſe children were in the ſame tranſgreſſion. The other crime objected is indeed more grievous, but very wrongfully put upon the Proteſtants, and that is the Murther of a certain Prieſt of <hi>Fenil,</hi> whereas it is generally known to the meaneſt perſons there, that not a drop of that blood can be aſperſed upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches. And if the Magiſtrate had thought any of the Proteſtants of <hi>Fenil</hi> in the leaſt wiſe guilty of that bloodſhed, he would not, I ſuppoſe, have baniſhed them with the reſt, but rather have caſt them into priſon,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98106:19"/> that they might have been puniſhed according to the heynouſneſſe of the fact: And therefore when all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>Fenil</hi> were promiſcuouſly commanded by <hi>Gaſtald</hi> to depart, and let go without taking notice of any man for ſo horrible a Crime, he thereby gave ſufficient teſtimony to the innocence of the Proteſtants in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And truly, in the Decree of baniſhment he makes not the leaſt mention of that horrid buſineſſe; but by declaring, thoſe perſons ſhould be exempted from baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that would abjure the Reformed Religion, he ſufficiently ſheweth, that the turning them out of all in the midſt of winter, at three daies warning, upon pain of death, was reſolved and executed to this end and purpoſe, that the men being reduced to harſhip and miſery, might by this means be compelled to a renouncing of their Religion. But put caſe that any man among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>Fenil</hi> had committed that wickedneſſe, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be concluded therefore that the reſt of them in <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nill,</hi> much leſſe that thoſe of the ſame Religion in <hi>Lucerne, Luſernette, Bobiane, St. John, la Tour, Briche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> and <hi>St. Second,</hi> ought in juſtice to be thruſt out of their ancient poſſeſſions; For, the guilt of this murther, though it had been committed by a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, it could by no means be imputed to theſe, or to any of the inhabitants of other Towns and Corporations that are farre diſtant from them. As by the Law of God and common Juſtice, ſo alſo by ſeveral Decrees of the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> made in favour of the Proteſtants, <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 29. 1603. and <hi>June,</hi> 4. 1653. it is prohibited, that the innocent ſhould not ſuffer for the guilty; ſo the Profeſſors of the Reformed Religion do not deſire to hinder, but make it their humble and earneſt Requeſt, that ſuch as are guilty may be brought to puniſhment.</p>
               <p>From hence then, it is obvious enough to any man, upon what account it is that the enemies of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurches have not onely driven very many of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their native Countrey and ancient dwellings into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98106:19"/> baniſhment, but goe on ſtil to perſecute them by a moſt cruel and bloody war; which they have cauſe to believe is not carried on againſt them by the proper inclination and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Prince himſelfe, but through the perſwaſion and inſtigation of the <hi>Congregation for propogating the Faith and extirpation of Hereticks,</hi> who have uſurped the cognizance of this Controverſie; being the onely perſons that have hindred the Proteſtants from being heard by the Prince, when they have preſented their Petitions, or made any Addreſſes to his Royal Highneſſe: But yet they ſo ordered the matter, that they directed divers Courtiers (their creatures) to feed the poore Proteſtants with hope that the eares of the Prince being wearied out with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Petitions, they might at length obtaine the favour to have their buſineſſe brought to a triall before competent Judges; while in the mean time they prepared Forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand, with which they make it their buſineſſe to fall upon them unawares and oppreſſe and deſtroy them. It is againſt this unjuſt violence that the Proteſtants endeavour to defend themſelves. They ſtruggle not againſt their Prince, but with the ſaid <hi>Congregation for extirpating He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> who as in the hearing and judging of this Cauſe, ſo alſo in the bloody execution of their ſentence by the ſword, have for the covering of their inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, made uſe of the name and Authority of the moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Prince.</p>
               <p>Moreover, they with the like injury blame thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>in the Valleys of Piedmont,</hi> about thoſe Letters of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion written on their behalf to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> by forrein Magiſtrates of the Reformed Religion, as if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied themſelves to States &amp; Princes abroad for protection, whereas thoſe Letters are no more but friendly offices, writtten without the privity of thoſe Churches, much leſſe upon their intreaty, and ſent by thoſe Magiſtrates of their own accord, induced thereto by a Pious and Zealous affection, and out of a brotherly commiſeration of that moſt grievous calamity, which might have moved even
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98106:20"/> ſtocks and ſtones, and whereof they had ſufficient notice from other Parts, ſeeing the turning of ſo many men, women, children, Infants, and ſick perſons, out of dores to the wide world in the midſt of winter, at three daies warning upon pain of death, was become a moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buſineſſe, which cried out aloud of it ſelf, and by reaſon of the wandring of thoſe miſerable Exiles, who were forced to rove up and down like vagabonds to beg their bread. Nor could they be ignorant how unjuſtly thoſe their Protaſtant brethren of the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont</hi> were oppreſſed by their Adverſaries in the <hi>Congregation for propagating the Faith,</hi> who had openly arrogated to themſelves the judging of the Cauſe of thoſe our brethren, in the Archbiſhop of <hi>Turin's</hi> houſe, contrary to all the Rules of judicial proceeding, and abuſed the Authority of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to oppreſſe and deſtroy them,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98106:20"/>
               <head>An Appendix to the foregoing Apologie.</head>
               <p>AS we are informed by ſeverall Letters, the ruine long intended by the enemies of the truth of the Churches of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of God, being angry becauſe of our ſinnes, is now executed. Indeed they had put off the execution by fained ſhewes and hopes of reconciliation, that they might the while provide all neceſſaries to compaſſe their ends; But againſt our expectation upon the 16. of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> 1655. the Army, made up of the Forces of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and of the King of <hi>France,</hi> amongſt which were ſome Iriſh Regiments, fell upon the Churches of the Valley of <hi>Lucerna,</hi> and with them the Militia of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and a crew of baniſhed theeves, felons, and other male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, let on purpoſe out of priſon, and from all parts flocking together in hope of prey; whoſe incurſions in an hoſtile manner the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed miſtruſting at firſt, and fearing to be cruſhed ere they could be heard, when all means of approach by ſupplication to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was taken from them, they withdrew themſelves into the mountaines. But the Commander of that Army, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Pianeſſe,</hi> ſewing the Fox skin to that of the Lyons, feigned he had no other intention
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98106:21"/> then to intreate the Reformed that they would approve to the Prince their faith and obedience, not by bare words, but by reall facts, <hi>viz.</hi> by quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering onely for three daies three Regiments of the Army, <hi>viz.</hi> one at <hi>Angrogne,</hi> another at <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> and a third at <hi>Boby;</hi> which if they did, he faithfully promiſed that no harme to them or theirs ſhould be done; which when it was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Reformed, and they had received the three Regiments, preſently the whole Army ruſhed upon them, no difference made of men, women, children, or ſucking babes, daſhing them againſt ſtones, ſome laying hold on them by the legges, and either diſmembring them, or hurling them headlong into precipices, with ſuch fury, that the very rocks were wet &amp; bloody with their brains, and that in ſight of the mothers, who after the murther committed upon their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were themſelves likewiſe murthered, as it was done in the Borrough of <hi>Villars</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> with ſuch horrible butchery, that ſome appeared to be indeed partakers of the croſſe of Chriſt, by being nailed to trees and put to lingring deaths: amongſt whom one <hi>Paul Clement,</hi> a man of a dvery upright life, who being nailed the head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ownward did undergoe with great conſtancy the butchery and continued in holy prayers to God to the very laſt; others, eſpecially of the weaker age and ſex, ſtriving to flie from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry of the ſouldiers, being driven through Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of pices into the mountaines full of ſnow, died of cold, and of other accidents; as the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98106:21"/> family of the L. <hi>Scipion Baſtia.</hi> In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of <hi>St. John</hi> and <hi>la Tour,</hi> they fell with fire and Sword upon Churches and private houſes; this holy fire being kindled by a Prieſt and a Franciſcan Frier, thereby to prove himſelfe a Seraphin with his St. <hi>Francis,</hi> to whom his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples give the ſeat of <hi>Lucifer.</hi> This diſaſter being made in the Churches of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the neighbour Valleys under the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> namely in that of <hi>Perouſe, St. Martine</hi> and <hi>Rupelate,</hi> as glorying at the thing done, commanded the Inhabitants of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in caſe they did not turn Papiſts, to leave the Countrey: Whereupon thoſe who perferred the richeſſes of Chriſt and Heaven to the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Country, chearfully went out, carrying his ſhame, and followed him in huge numbers. The names of the baniſhed, who perſevered in the faith, and how many they be, are not yet known to us; for thoſe of <hi>Lucerne</hi> having been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed unawares, they made an eſcape and fled where they could. Of many thouſands, a very few have carried any thing with them, whereby they might for ſome daies preſerve life. Thoſe that remaine doe by the bowels of Chriſt beſeech all godly men to open their hearts unto them, that they may receive of him a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and may reap ſo much the greater harveſt, that the field of God to receive ſeed, is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98106:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Abſtract of a Letter writen from the Vale of</hi> Perouſe <hi>the</hi> 17 <hi>of</hi> April 1655. <hi>Deſcribing the beginning of the murders and cruelties committed on the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OUr teares which are no longer of water but of blood, and doe not onely offuſcate our ſight, but doe alſo ſuffocate our poor hearts, and cauſe us to hold our pens with a trembling hand, as they are led by braines, not onely dulled by the blowes, they juſt now received, but alſo extreamly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the new alarms and aſſaults made on us, doe hinder us from framing ſuch Letters as we could wiſh, and ſuch as the ſtrangeneſſe of our deſolations ſhould require. But we doe intreate you to excuſe us and to gather from among our ſobbings the ſenſe of what we ſhould be willing to expreſſe unto you. Notwithſtanding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports ſpred abroad that we would not ſtoope to make our addreſſes to his Royal Highneſſe, about the moleſtations raiſed againſt us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you have had notice, Yet we never ceaſed from writing, petitioning, and ſending of Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; But all the while, as formerly, wee have been referred, ſometimes to the Counſell <hi>de propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandâ</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98106:22"/> 
               <hi>fide,</hi> ſometimes to the Marquis <hi>de Planneſs.</hi> The three laſt times they were flatly refuſed audience, under pretence they had not Letters of atturney ſufficiently authoriſing them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and accept of whatſoever his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhould be pleaſed to offer. And eſpecially at the inſtigation, and by means of the Romiſh Clergy an Army of five or ſix thouſand men was ſecretly raiſed, who unexpectedly fell upon <hi>St. John</hi> and <hi>la Tour,</hi> being encouraged by the preſence of the ſaid Marquis <hi>de Pianneſſe,</hi> who having ſeized on the ſaid places, was preſently reinforced, not onely by all ſuch among our neighbours, as were able to bear armes, but by the whole <hi>Piedmont,</hi> where it having been ſpred abroad, that our goods were given to be plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, they came all upon us with ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous fury, and chiefly a crue of baniſhed rogues, priſoners and guilty perſons, upon hope of ſaving their own ſouls and filling their pockets. It was not all, that they might the better oppreſſe us, five or ſix regiments of the French Army were ſent againſt us, beſides the Iriſh, to whom, they ſay our country is given to poſſeſſe it, and other forces that are coming up daily towards us, under pretence of taking quarters and refreſhing themſelves in the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys. That innumerable number of men, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the licentiouſneſſe of the Marquis <hi>de Pianneſſe,</hi> being ſtirred up by the Monks, and led and ſet on by our bad neighbours, hath ſo ſurprized us on all ſides and with ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98106:23"/> violence, yea and with ſuch a dreadful trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſpecially in <hi>Engrogne, Villar</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> to whom the ſaid Marquis had engaged his word, that if they would but quarter for three daies a regiment in each place or Commonalty, they would have no harme, that in a moment all hath been brought to confuſion, and the Inhabitants having done ſomewhat towards the ſaving of their Temples a little lower from the fury of the <hi>Boutefeux,</hi> were forced to flie for ſaving their Wives and children, not onely thoſe of the plaine, who were retired into the Mountains, but alſo the Inhabitants of the ſaid Mountains themſelves, ſeeing they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied and ſurprized at the back door. Yet they could not uſe ſuch diligence, but that many of them were overtaken in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as among the reſt at <hi>Villar</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> where they were kept in without any poſſibility of ſaving their lives, the enemies having poſſeſſed themſelves of the Fort of <hi>Mirebouc</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to hinder them from ſaving of themſelves, and an horrid maſſacre was done on them. In a certain place or corner they villanouſly tormented one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifthty women and ſmall children, and having cut off their heads, they daſhed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt the Rocks; and the priſoners they took, who were fifthteen years of age and upwards, who would not yeild to go to Maſſe, were hanged by them, or nailed to ſome trees the feet upwards, which torments they conſtantly and reſolutely endured. We hear
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98106:23"/> that thoſe of quality have been carried to <hi>Turin,</hi> as among the reſt one of our poor Brethren Mr. <hi>Gros</hi> Miniſter and part of his family.</p>
            <p>In the vale of <hi>Luſerne</hi> there is neither booty nor cattel left: What hath been ſaved from the plunder is very little; the reſt hath furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſeveral Towns of the enemies in <hi>Piedmont:</hi> As to the moveables they have all been loſt alſo. There are ſome whole Commonalties, as thoſe of <hi>St. John</hi> and <hi>la Tour,</hi> where not one houſe hath eſcaped the fire, nor their Temples nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the firing of them all hath been mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a <hi>Franciſcan Fryer</hi> and a Prieſt. Among thoſe deſolations the mother hath loſt her childe, the husband his wife, the richeſt are brought to beggery, and in great ſorrow; and are ſo much the farther from being comforted that ſome Churches being yet left untouched in the vale of <hi>Perouſe</hi> and <hi>St. Martin</hi> which was a refuge to thoſe that were perfecuted, this day they have received a command to be gone out of hand, under pain of death, namely thoſe that are within the dominions of his Royal Highneſſe, having no longer time but to be gone immediately.</p>
            <p>However, theſe our fine floriſhing and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Churches are loſt without reſſource, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept God be pleaſed to work wonders for them: Our time is come, our meaſure was full. But take pitty of the ruines of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and lament for the wound of the poor <hi>Joſeph;</hi> but above all have a real compaſſion, opening
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98106:24"/> your bowels to many thouſands of perſons brought to poverty and beggery, for having been deſirous to follow the Lamb whereſoever he goes. Sirs and moſt deare Fathers and Brothers, you have ever been as a ſacred anchor, to whom after God our poor Churches have had recourſe in their afflictions; take pitty on them for Gods ſake, at this time, when they have not felt the rod, but the Iron barre, in doing and procuring ſome good, both to the Paſtors and to the ſheep, who are ſcattered; working for them according to your wiſdome, and that as ſpeedily as you can or think fit. We expect that grace from your goodneſſe, commending our ſelves and our poor ſcattered flocks to your holy prayers, praying to God that he might be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to preſerve you, and to proſper your holy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98106:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Lyon, the</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of May</hi> 1655.</head>
            <p>THe perſecutors at the firſt aſſault having loſt moſt of their men by the couragious reſiſtance of our men, they were out of hopes to compaſſe their deſigne by open force. Their Head diſſembled his evill will, and made a ſhew as if hee had received or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Prince to ſpare theſe poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to promiſe them, from his part a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for what was paſt; provided for the time to come they ſhould prove wiſer and better ſubjects, and on condition that they ſhould preſently quarter in the Valleys ſome Forces that were about <hi>Pinerol,</hi> both of the French Army, and of that of his Royall Highneſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Valleys having conſulted, they were adviſed to accept of that unlucky condition, which they did; and aſſoon as the ſaid forces were come into the place aſſigned unto them for their quarters, they were commanded to ſeize on all the paſſages and avenues, and to make an end of our people, which they were ready to execute, becauſe of the booty they hoped to have; ſo that they killed and plundered whatſoever they met with, without diſtinction
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98106:25"/> of women or children. Four Elders and among them Mr. <hi>Paul de Roſſane,</hi> as Pious and Religious a man as ever I knew, were hanged at <hi>la Tour;</hi> eighteen men, and among them Mr. <hi>Gros,</hi> a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, were carried priſoners to <hi>Turin;</hi> and thoſe who could eſcape that deſolation, are fled towards the <hi>Dauphine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:98106:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Continuation of the deſcription of the murthers, and cruelties committed on the Reformed, in the Valleys of</hi> Piedmont, <hi>on the</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 7. <hi>of</hi> Aprill 1655.</head>
            <p>MY Lord Marqueſs of <hi>Pianeſs,</hi> having many times reiterated to the Deputies of the Churches of the Valleys with aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veration (as they do affirm) that upon the Paroll of his Royall Highneſs and his own (they giving teſtimony of their confidence and obedience, by the Reception of ſuch Regiments) they ſhould not receive any injury, They did thereupon ſuffer them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without any reſiſtance whatſoever, hoping the rather that it ſhould have been ſo, ſeeing thoſe places were reſerved, even in the order lately publiſhed, and never queſtioned, as to their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, But thoſe of St. <hi>John,</hi> who had all their goods and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in <hi>Angrogne,</hi> and for whom there was no Quarter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted thither to ſave their Wives and Children, which alſo did thoſe of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> who ſoon perceived the Treachery, and how the Papiſts keep Faith to the pretended Hereticks. The ſaid Marqueſs alſo kept Priſoners the Deputies of St. <hi>John</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grogne,</hi> who went thither to treat upon his Parole; and as the Troops agreed on, were going up by the way appointed, three or four thouſand men got before them by a backway, near <hi>La Tour,</hi> climbing up with an incomparable ſwiftneſs, putting all to the Sword they met with, and firing the Houſes of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> near the Meadow of <hi>La Tour,</hi> being one of the ſtrongeſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and at the furtheſt diſtance; and that they executed even before the others were come into the middle of <hi>Angrogne</hi> which they had choſen for their Quarter. The other Troops did the like neer St. <hi>John</hi> towards <hi>Bricheras,</hi> and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces near <hi>la Tour,</hi> ſo long as Day light permitted.</p>
            <p>Amongſt ſo many furious aſſaults, ſo many violent attempts, and ſo black deceits and treaſons, the air being all on fire by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98106:26"/> reaſon of the flames, or all duskiſh by the ſmoak of burnt Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Churches, did reſound nothing elſe but the Cries, Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and fearful ſcriechings, made yet more pitiful by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thoſe Eccho's, which are in thoſe Mountains and Rocks.</p>
            <p>The Mother hath loſt her ſucking Child, the Husband his Wife, the Brother his Brother, ſome have been barbarouſly maſſacred, whilſt they were buſy in ſaving ſome of their goods, others having fled to eſcape to the tops of the Mountains, were forced to caſt themſelves into the hollows of Rocks, and amongſt the Snow, without fire, without nouriſhment, without covering, ſick, old, wounded, Women with Child, of whom many miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and lay dead near their Children, after they had ſuſtained themſelves with a little Snow, which was put and melted in their mouths inſtead of Sugar. Amongſt many, who were forced to run away bare-foot and bare-legg'd, ſeverall perſons of great quality had their legs and feet ſo long frozen by Snow and Ice, that they have altogether loſt them.</p>
            <p>On the morrow after, being the 21. the Boutefeus and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers were not idle: A Monk of the Order of St. <hi>Francis</hi> and a Prieſt, who were deſirous to have the honour to be the chief Incendiaries, with their fire works (which they eaſily could do) did not fail to ſet on fire the Church of St. <hi>John,</hi> and almoſt all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining houſes, part in <hi>Angrogne,</hi> and part in <hi>La Tour.</hi> And where they found any Corner free from the firſt fires, the Prieſt did but diſcharge his Carbine to make an end of in; And the Souldiers being fleſhed with blood, did run to the very tops of the Rocks and places, which ſeemed to be inacceſſible, to cut the throats of all ſuch as they ſhould find there. It was not a difficult thing to them ſo to do, ſince they were not in a poſture to make any other reſiſtance, but by their tears, which might have cauſed the moſt barbarous Tartarians and Canniballs, to let fall their Arms out of their hands. At <hi>Taillareta</hi> very ſmall Village ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d upon one of the higheſt hills of <hi>La Tour,</hi> they offered a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand injuries to an hundred and fifty Women and little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and then cut off their heads; whereof they did boyl many,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98106:26"/> and eat their Brains, but left off, ſaying, they were too unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, and that it went againſt their Stomack; they cut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others in pieces and bits, which they threw the one at the other. From a poor woman that eſcaped them, and is yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, although ſhe was cruelly treated by them, they took her little Child in ſwadling Bands, and threw him from a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice with many others. And there have been many others, who have been torn and ſplit in the middle by two Souldiers, who took thoſe innocent Creatures, one by one leg, and the other by the other, and after they had torn each one his half, they beat one another with it. They ſtripp'd naked many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, without diſtinction either of age or ſex, and cut their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies after ſuch a manner, as would make one tremble to hear it recited, and then threw upon them Salt and Gunpowder, and then putting on them their Shirts again, they ſet them on fire, making them burn upon theſe poor martyrized Bodies. Others being naked were tyed Neck and Heels together, and rowled down ſome Precipices. They were ſo barbarous as not to exempt one <hi>Peter Symond</hi> of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> being 100 years old, nor his wife, who was 95 years; They burnt a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in their houſes, refuſing to kill them before, though they requeſted it: To others they opened their Breaſts; to others they pulled out their Guts, and cut off their privy parts; After they had abuſed ſeverall women, they thruſt many ſtones in their privy parts, and walked them in this poſture till they dyed. They hanged others upon trees by the feet, and left them in that eſtate till they dyed. They gaunched many both by the fundament after the Turkiſh manner, and a Croſs. They ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked others through the Belly to the ground, and drove the Stakes into the earth as far as they could. Of thoſe whom they brought alive before the Marqueſs, and who would not abjure their Religion, they carried many to <hi>Turin,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others Maſter <hi>Groſs,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Aghit,</hi> Miniſters of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> and that after they had ſeen the admirable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>John Paillas,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Paul Clement,</hi> that a poor Peaſant, this an Elder and Deacon of the Church of <hi>La Tour,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98106:27"/> the former having choſen the Gibbet rather than the Maſſe, the other was carried neer him to appale him; but as he was on the top of the Ladder, and the Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries redoubling their exhortations, ſaying, it was yet time enough if he would turn Catholike, he ſpake to the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner to do his duty, deſiring him to diſpatch, and prayed God to pardon thoſe Murtherers, although (ſaid he) he ſaw, as preſent, the Vengeance that God wou'ld take for ſo much innocent blood ſpilt.</p>
            <p>My pen falls from my hand in deſcribing theſe things; yea, the very thoughts of them makes my whole Body to tremble, my Hair to ſtand up; A Heart of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, a hand of ſteel, and a pen of Iron, could not expreſs halfe the horrid Prodigies of cruelty and lamentable ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles which were ſeen, unheard of amongſt the moſt barbarous in former ages, farre from ever being exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Chriſtendome. You might have ſeen here the legg of a Woman, there the head of a Child, ſometimes the privy Members of a man, the Intrails of another, and ſometimes the pieces of another, whom the Beaſts had not yet made an end of eating. Tears obſcure my ſight, and the violence of my ſobbings hinders me from procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further.</p>
            <p>Having pauſed here a litle and taken breath, I ſhall ſay farther, that a poor old man, being ninety five years old, called Mr. <hi>Thomas Margher,</hi> having been taken among the reſt, a French Officer, who was preſent at his Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, relates of him, that at the firſt time he refuſed to go to Maſſe, his Noſe was cut off; then being asked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain whether he would go to Maſſe, and having anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he would rather chooſe to dye, one of his Eares was cut off, and then the other; and ſo every time he ſaid he would not go to the Maſſe, one or other of his Limbs was cut off; at length they hanged him as they did the other two above named: and then this good old man with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98106:27"/> a ſmiling countenance would ſay to his Executioners, <hi>Do ye tye and torment my Body as much as you pleaſe, yet you cannot touch my Soul, nor have ye any Priſons or Chains that can keep it from going to Heaven; but to the contrary according to the courſe of Nature, having ſo little time yet to live in this VVorld, ye do but haſten my Deliverance and my Happineſs.</hi> Then having given thanks to God for the honor he did him to ſuffer for his name, he prayed the Hangman to performe his duty.</p>
            <p>Of the ſpoil of Proviſions, of Wine ſpilt in abundance by thoſe who pull'd off the iron hoops from the veſſells, of the Cattell, or of their plunder, ſay we any thing; The very Women came from the furtheſt part of <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> and carryed away all to the very Broomes.</p>
            <p>A very few of them, who made ſhift to get away with ſome of their Cattell, upon the neighbouring Mountains of <hi>Val Perouſe,</hi> ſav'd ſome of them there, all the reſt were plundred. The <hi>French, Iriſh, Piemontois,</hi> baniſhed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and releaſed Criminalls, divided the Spoil amongſt themſelves, and many of them killed one another in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of it; That which they could not carry away they ſet on fire, and thoſe poor people that eſcaped as Brands reſcued from the fire, the one almoſt as rich as the other, being of <hi>Val Perouſe, Val Cluſon</hi> and <hi>Queiras,</hi> ſome of them drawing lamentably after them their miſerable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies with Cries and Tears, others weeping and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing the loſſe of theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Val Luſerne</hi> was deſtroyed, which did contain 7 Churches, each containing about three or foure thouſand perſons, except <hi>Roche-platt</hi> and <hi>Roras,</hi> which had ſomething leſs. Before the Troops aſſaulted the reſt, the Deputies of the Vallies deſired the protection &amp; interceſſion of Monſieur <hi>de la Bertoniere.</hi> Lieutenant &amp; Governor for his Majeſty at <hi>Pineroll,</hi> and of Monſieur <hi>de Corſelles,</hi> Captain in the Regiment of <hi>Navarr,</hi> who ſaid he had found in their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98106:28"/> Royal Highneſſes a great inclination to pity, deſired them to intercede for them, which they did with a great deal of Diligence, and preſented their Petition to his Royall Highneſs, and at the ſame time gave their Letters to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Pyaneſſa,</hi> to whom (as they were inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) however things went, all would be referred.</p>
            <p>The Contents of the Letter ſhew's that of the Petition to wit.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Excellent Lords.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PReſuming that neer the infinite clemency of his Royal Higneſs, there may be yet ſome Grace and Mercy for us, his poor and diſconſolate Subjects upon our due humility and ſubmiſſion to him, we have ſent to him our Petition in the beſt form the preſent diſturbances will permit us, referring our ſelves wholly to his good pleaſure, and promiſing to conform our ſelves to whatever he ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, if he will onely give us leave to enjoy the liberty of our Conſciences, ſo that we may ſerve God according to his Word; in the mean time we ſupplicate his Highneſs that it would pleaſe him to cauſe theſe ſtrange Hoſtilities to ceaſe, which are committed againſt his intention, and alſo your Excellencies; Of which we thought it our duty, not onely to give advice to your Excellency, but alſo as to one that hath full Power and Authority, and to whom we are informed all ſhall be referred: We make to you the ſame Supplications and Promiſes, imploring your Grace and Protection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at <hi>Val Cluſon</hi> 
                        <date>the third. of <hi>May</hi> 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Excellencies moſt humble, moſt obedient and devoted ſervants, the Deputies of the Vallies of</hi> Luſern, Perouſe, <hi>and St.</hi> Martin.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <argument>
                     <p>It was ſigned by a great number.</p>
                  </argument>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98106:28"/>
            <p> Let the Reader take notice that theſe poor people, for to endeavour to preſerve yet this ſmall part of <hi>Val Perouſe,</hi> which belongs to his Royall Highneſs, with the ſmall and poor Vally of St. <hi>Martin</hi> (notwithſtanding their entire and irreproveable ſidelity and innocence) did humble themſelves, but all to no purpoſe as yet, except God be pleaſed to touch the Hearts of the Superiours, or deliver them by other means</p>
            <p>Every one doth ask, <hi>But what may be the reaſon theſe poor folk have been ſo dealt with?</hi> Farre from hence rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons enough and cauſes of it are alledged; whereof they do not ſo much as ſpeak of upon the place.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Some ſay that the Reformed have killed a Prieſt at Fenill in the lower Vale of</hi> Luſerne; But that Prieſt hath been killed but ſixteen daies after publication of the aforeſaid Edict, and was murthered by the Secretary of the Prefect of that Province, who is a Romiſh Catholike, and had already ſlain another Prieſt in the ſame place. A young man of the Reformed Religion, having been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have been partaker with him therein, hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the ſaid, Reformed into the hands of Juſtice and of the Delegate of his Royall Highneſs; who having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed there, that the ſaid Secretary called <hi>Pagot</hi> had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him to go along with him in that horrid executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, promiſed to give him three hundred Piſtolls, but that he had refuſed to do it, and took onely two, to bind him not to ſay a word of it, hath been releaſed and declared not guilty. After this, conſidering the ſcruples of ſome yet, the ſame man hath ſeverall times preſented himſelfe to Madame Royall and the cheifeſt of her Miniſters, and the Reformed have ſtill repreſented him upon all occaſions to be examined and brought face to face before the parties, but they ſtill refuſed it, holding him as fully juſtified, and the other convicted. Beſides, though among the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed there ſhould have been found a Thiefe, neither
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98106:29"/> their Conceſſions nor their Laws do ſuffer the innocent to be puniſhed for the guilty. Such Aſſaſſinations were never commited by order of the Reformed, and could have no advantage by the death of an inconſiderable Country Prieſt, who could never do them neither good or evill.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Some ſay that at</hi> La Tour <hi>an Aſſe hath been dreſſed like a Monk.</hi> It is a Diabolicall invention. In a word it was thus. The Youth of the place, partly Papiſts, partly Reformed, to jeere and mock at a very Heterocliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Marriage, made a <hi>Charivary,</hi> as they call it, and tooke the Aſſe of the Bridegroome, whom they did ſet on the topp of the Oven in a publick place, where it was ſeen of all, all the day long; and nothing therein touched the Monks, nor the Maſſe, nor the Hoſt. The Roman Catholikes in ſuch occaſions have often ſet up Aſſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of their Pinacles in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Therefore the publiſhed Order alledges no ſuch reaſons, onely the Marqueſſe <hi>de Pianneſa,</hi> as appears in the anſwer he got M. <hi>Gibeline</hi> (the Roman Catholike At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney of the the Reformed at <hi>Turin)</hi> to make, ſaid, that his Royall Highnes <hi>was willing to abaſe their pride, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving craved the Protection of the Forraign Princes,</hi> becauſe the Lords of <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Berne,</hi> after the Order publiſhed againſt them (though not required, but out of their own inclinations) had ſent to his Royall Highnes ſome Letters in their behalf. <hi>Let the Reader judge of the validity of this Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Fourth is moſt cryed up in <hi>Piedmont. viz. That the Reformed have cruelly murthered the Catholiques in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and have wholly expelled them; and that they ought to murther the Reformed in</hi> Piedmont, <hi>and clear the State of them, to lodge the</hi> Iriſh <hi>in their place.</hi> Let yet the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98106:29"/> Reader judge of this reaſon. Beſides it is falſe the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med have murthered the Catholicks in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Therfore it remains that there hath been no other true cauſe of this, but the haued they bear to the Religion; it being known to all the world, that no Subjects have ever been true or more obedient to their Prince than they, who never ſtirred, when all the reſt of the State was up in Arms; who ſtill payd their Taxes, though ever burthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, have borne extraordinary Winter Quarters, aflor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their men for the war, as often as demanded, and even ſome few days afore their deſolation, ſent their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litias for the ſervice of his Royall Highneſs, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of his very firſt command.</p>
            <p>I have haſtily given you a Copy, of this tract, of the horrible furies of the Adverſaries, deſiring you to ſee if his Highneſs, the Sereniſſime Lord Protector, could take occaſion to inſert in the Treaty with <hi>France,</hi> the re-eſtabliſhment of our Brethren eſcaped from the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, which they have cauſed the Iriſh to do, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of their being baniſhed out of their Country, for Maſſacring the Proteſtants there. Your Brother hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured us, he will give us the Charity ordained by your Church, A generall Collection in your Quarters will be neceſſary, there being ſo many thouſands deſpoild of all, that are ſeeking for refuge. There are two Miniſters <hi>viz.</hi> Maſter <hi>Groſs</hi> and Maſter <hi>Aghi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Priſoners at <hi>Turin,</hi> God ſtrengthen and deliver them, and conſerve you and your Colleagues, whom I ſalute,</p>
            <closer>remaining
<date>
                  <hi>May</hi> 8. 1655.</date>
               <signed>Moſt honoured Brother, wholy yours.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written to his Highneſs the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. about the ſaid Murthers Maſſacres and cruelties, ſent together with the ſaid deſcriptions.</head>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98106:30"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>To his Highneſs My Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough his Highneſe the Lord Protector be well informed of whatſoever comes to paſs in moſt places of the world, yet we have thought he would not be ſorry to ſee, as in a contracted picture, the horrid cruelties pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Duke of <hi>Savoy's</hi> men, upon the Faithfull in the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont;</hi> That is to ſay, upon ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that, if any in the world, did live in the greateſt purity, and the greateſt innocency; whoſe onely crime is, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, nor their Fathers, nor their Aunceſtors, 500 years ſince, would ever pollute themſelves with the Roman Superſtitions and Idolatries.</p>
            <p>The whole Chriſtendome have their eyes fixed on his Highneſs, and all good men hope that he will avenge, or rather God will avenge, by his hand, ſuch a helliſh barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs. If we ſhould have a leſs knowledge of his Zeal, and of his Heroicall courage, we would tell him what once <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſaid to the Queen<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Eſther, If thou holdeſt thy peace at this time, then ſhall their enlargement and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance ariſe from another place; But thou and thy Father's houſe ſhall be deſtroyed: And who knoweth whether thou art come to ſuch a high dignity for ſuch a time as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at his Highneſs poſſeſſes lights altogether extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, he will of himſelf conſider that God hath given him a great power, to imploy it to his glory; and that he hath put a victorious ſword in his hand, <hi>to be a revenger to execute wrath upon thoſe that do evill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> So that, as ſince the Greation of the World, nothing hath been ſeen ſo dreadfull, ſo nothing ſhall be puniſhed in ſuch an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary manner.</p>
            <p>It is hoped that with him ſeverall Proteſtant Princes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98106:30"/> will imbrace ſo juſt a cauſe. But if there be any that be not ſenſibly moved by ſo deep and ſo ſharp a wound, and that having power, yet be not willing to proſecute and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thoſe Martherers, and thoſe Incendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries, that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will be applyed unto them of the Propheteſs <hi>Deborah, Curſe ye</hi> Meroz <hi>curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord with the mighty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges c.</hi> 5 <hi>v.</hi> 2 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean while, your Highneſs will ſpread through the whole earth the ſweet ſavour of his name, and as it hath been ſaid, <hi>The ſword of the Lord and of</hi> Gideon, ſo hereafter they will ſay, <hi>the ſword of the Lord and of</hi> OLIVER. His praiſes will be celebrated to the world's end, and they will ſay that the Protector of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> is become the Protector of all thoſe that are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake.</p>
            <p>All thoſe that do ſincerely love God, and that are ſick becauſe of the bruiſe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> will heartily pray unto God, that he might be pleaſed to prolong the days of his, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſettle his Government, and to pour upon his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity his moſt holy and moſt precious bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Let his Highneſs be aſſured that this draught hath been made by a faithfull hand, and let him have the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not to enquire who he is that ſends it. It is not ſo much the voice of men, or the blood of the Martyrs, as the voice of God himſelf, who crys for vengeance for the injury done to his great name, and who commands him to work the deliverance of thoſe that are Priſoners for the Lord Jeſus, and to reſtore to their Native Country the poor baniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d men, who like the faithfull of old, are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the wildern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſes, in the Dens, in the Mountains and in the clefts of the earth: That they might ſing as thoſe that returned from the Babylonian Captivity, <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity of</hi> Zion, <hi>we were like them that dream: Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. <hi>v.</hi> 1. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
